Hi, everyone. Welcome to Practical Python. My name is Nina Zacharenko and I'm your instructor today.
This is an immersive hands-on Python course and it requires a little bit of prerequisite knowledge.
So in order to really succeed today, you should be comfortable on the command line. You not have to be a pro.
And you should know a little bit about programming in some other language. So understand basic constructs like loops and variables.
And those are going to be the things that set you on the path to success.
If you're a little bit more of a beginner, you might enjoy the two-day course that I did for front-end masters last year called Introduction to Python and Python Fundamentals.
Now, you might see this course website that I have up here. You can find this at practical.learnpython.dev.
Let me bring that URL up for a minute.
Practical.learnpython.dev.
Now, I recommend that you don't just follow along on this website. Don't read because we're going to be moving pretty quickly today.
And you're going to get most comfortable if you type along with me.
So by typing along with me as I type, you're going to gain that muscle memory that's really going to help that knowledge stick.
A little bit about me.
My name is Nina Zackarenko and let's see here.
I've been coding all together for probably about a decade now.
I started out in Java. That is my secret.
But I moved towards Python probably about six years ago now because I really liked the community.
And I thought that the libraries and the ecosystem were really amazing.
I started speaking at Python conferences and just completely fell in love with it.
Recently, I've been elected to the board of directors for the Python software foundation, which is really great.
I get to do a lot of good work.
And I've also written code for companies like Reddit and Meetup and HBO.
These days, I'm a principal cloud advocate at Microsoft focusing on Python.
If you want to stay in touch with me, I'm on Twitter or LinkedIn or GitHub, all of the links are here.
And then I also included links to some of the more popular conference talks that I've done over the years.
You can also find my other courses on front and masters.
One of my personal favorites is get in depth and as well as Python fundamentals and intermediate Python.
A little bit about navigating the course.
If you see any typos, which I have not made because I'm 100% perfect.
But if you spot anything that you think shouldn't be there, there's an edit this page link at the top of every page.
And that will take you directly to GitHub where you can open a pull request.
There are navigation arrows here on the left and the right side.
And you can also navigate by keyboard shortcuts, which is one of my favorite features.
There are bread crumbs on the top left here for each section.
And that will pull up a table of contents right here.
Some sections look like this with double arrows that have additional contents.
So you can just go ahead and click on that and that content will expand.
If you want to copy any of the code or any of the commands, you can hit this button right here and it will copy to the clipboard.
If we're working in the Python repo, for example, where there are extra control characters that are in that will be displayed on the course website,
know that they won't be copied over.
You can search in this text box up here.
And as you go through the course, you'll see a little checkbox next to each chapter.
You can go ahead and clear the history if you find that distracting.
And again, I really suggest following along with me in the class and typing as much as possible.
This is a resource for you to have because I know that when I'm done with the class, especially when that's all day,
I feel like, oh, did I learn anything?
I'm just going to forget everything.
So it's here for you for afterwards.
It's here for the exercises or if you need to go back and figure out how to do something.
But I do not recommend reading it.
I want to quickly go through the course agenda.
So I'm going to explain to you why Python.
Why you might want to reach for Python.
Why you might want to choose Python for your project and talk a little bit about some of the philosophies and Python's design principles.
Then we're going to move on to data types.
Python is a dynamic language.
What does that mean?
We're going to learn how to work with numbers, strings, lists, and more.
Then we're going to move on to some of the more advanced data types that Python offers,
and those are sets, tuples, and dictionaries.
These are container objects that let us organize other types of objects in different ways into other kinds of data structures.
Then we're going to move on to functions, loops, and logic.
Functions help us organize our code in a way that's more readable and reusable,
and they accept arguments and defaults as needed.
And loops are going to take us, let us take action on collections of different items.
Boolean logic is going to allow us to control the flow of our program.
We're going to cover some practical applications of what we've learned so far,
including using advanced looping types like list comprehension,
converting between different types and Python, which I believe is really one of its absolute strengths.
And we're also going to cover how to work with files.
Next is going to be object-oriented Python, which allows us to represent our code in a little bit of a different way.
We can define reusable classes and define relationships between different objects,
and build modular and reusable code.
We're also going to cover libraries and modules.
So now that you have all the foundational understanding of how Python works,
you're going to learn how to structure your code and work with different libraries,
both the standard library and external third-party packages.
And then in the last chapter, we're going to cover bug frameworks,
and we're going to talk about Django in particular.
So we're going to practice all of our new Python knowledge by building a basic blog,
a basic web application with some unit tests and a database.
This is going to give you a great tour of everything that's available in Python.
You might not be an expert in any one of these areas by the end of the day,
but you will have the tools available to learn and discover more.
Now, there are a few prerequisites for going through the course.
You need to have a Linux Mac or Windows 10 machine.
If you're using Windows 10, you need to make sure that you have administrative rights
so that you can run your programs correctly.
We're going to be working with the latest version of Python,
which as of today is Python 39.
We're going to be using Visual Studio Code and the Python extension for Visual Studio Code.
Now, a lot of you are already programming.
You already have your environments set up.
Why VS Code?
Well, I recommend that we're all on the same environment today,
because if you run into any issues,
this is really going to help us troubleshoot and figure out what's wrong.
Once you're done with the class, feel free to go back to your editor of choice.
I have a section here for how to set up VS Code with different key bindings.
For example, I use VS Code with Emacs key bindings,
and you can set up them or sublime or whatever you're most comfortable with.
Really appreciate if we were all in the same environment,
and that way you can follow the steps and you know there's nothing about your machine
or your editor that's going to cause any problems.
I'm going to review the set up instructions for Mac OS,
because that's what I'm using, but instructions for Windows are available as well.
And then I'm going to quickly show you how to configure VS Code
for maximum productivity and Python.
Alright, so here are all the things that you should have downloaded and set up.
Python 3 Visual Studio Code and the Python extension for Visual Studio Code.
If you don't have these set up right now,
please go ahead and start installing these prerequisites on your machine
while I continue talking.